<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>stem | Walker Blackston</title>
    <link>https://walkerblackston.com/tag/stem/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://walkerblackston.com/tag/stem/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>stem</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://walkerblackston.com/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>stem</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/tag/stem/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>STEM Grad School Boot-camp: Week 3</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://casualinferencedotorg.files.wordpress.com/2020/02/bootcamp-2.jpeg?w=480&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This will be part 3 of 4 in a &lt;strong&gt;weekly series&lt;/strong&gt; focused on preparing for graduate school in STEM if you come from a humanities based undergrad or other graduate experience. Please make sure to follow my blog to get the latest update to the series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;We must believe that we are gifted for something and that this thing, at whatever cost, must be attained.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; - Marie Curie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impetus for a &amp;ldquo;big project&amp;rdquo; has pushed even the most stuck thinkers and writers of our time into the realm of productivity. While the particulars of each approach differ- JK Rowlings used to book luxury hotel rooms for the self-imposted financial pressure- the common thread of a &amp;ldquo;big project&amp;rdquo; remains. I propose that this type of project would exponentially improve your graduate experience (and subsequent job hunt). This week, we will be planning out our &amp;ldquo;big project,&amp;rdquo; or the one thing that if you finished it this semester or academic year would confer immense benefits to your career. This project comes with &lt;strong&gt;just two basic ground rules&lt;/strong&gt; that, if followed, should confer these exponential benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) It should be both easy to describe and plan but hard to execute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you are weeks from starting your STEM graduate experience, the precision of your planning should be ramping up. We&amp;rsquo;ve covered everything from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://casual-inference.org/2020/02/03/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;existential&lt;/a&gt; to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://casual-inference.org/2020/02/12/stem-bootcamp-week-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mundane&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s time to put pen to paper. &lt;strong&gt;Take out a sheet of paper or open your journal and write down the following:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;what would I be most proud of myself for doing this year?&lt;/em&gt; Make sure this is related to graduate school, but not necessarily grades or GPA focused. By this, I mean, try not to write about getting a 4.0. While this is a great accomplishment, most employers and even PhD programs think in terms of grade bands. A 4.0 is nice, but not as weighty as it was in undergrad. It might be expected in some rare instances or institutions (check first), but a 3.5-3.7 may carry similar assurances of competency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;focus on planning something that the other students (who are chasing the 4.0) are not considering&lt;/strong&gt;. Can you get on a peer-reviewed scientific manuscript or conference abstract? Can you co-write a computer program with an advisor or advanced PhD student? Are there skills that are not being taught in your program you could pick up and organize into a brief seminar for faculty and staff? These are flexible win-wins - even the &lt;em&gt;efforts&lt;/em&gt; to produce deliverables as code or a paper increase your skills in the area and often lead to better letters of recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) It&amp;rsquo;s what you work on first.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This next rule will certainly get me in trouble with your advisor and lecturers. However, if executed properly, should leave you in good shape for their classes in addition to your goals. This project should be the focus of that first chunk of study time during the day. When you are fresh and most likely to hang on to your attention , this time period becomes critical to advance the goals of your project. Even if you are in a lull and waiting on feedback from others, commit 30 minutes to planning your next moves. How will you approach feedback from this person? Should you meet with them personally (or over Skype) to discuss? Make a schedule to chip away and make your big project seem smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/em&gt; If planned carefully and attacked consistently, the big project could catapult your STEM graduate school experience into career success. Many careers follow exponential curves for success - marginal gains creep forward from hard work until they explode into life-altering achievement. The &amp;ldquo;big project&amp;rdquo; is a way to skip the plateau phase. In the same way that grants beget more grants, papers beget more papers and scientific expertise begets more scientific expertise. Make the moonshots now and you will reap rewards later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stay tuned for the &lt;strong&gt;final week of STEM Grad school boot-camp,&lt;/strong&gt; where we will be fine tuning some day-to-day habits guaranteed to transition you fully from humanities to STEM!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STEM Grad School Bootcamp: Week 2</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-bootcamp-week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 15:17:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-bootcamp-week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://casual-inference.org/2020/02/25/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;STEM Grad School Boot-camp: Week 3 – Casual Inferences&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;time datetime=&#34;2020-02-25 10:30:16&#34;&gt;Feb 2, 2020&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] of your planning should be ramping up. We’ve covered everything from the existential to the mundane. It’s time to put pen to paper. Take out a sheet of paper or open your journal and write down […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STEM Grad School Bootcamp: Week 2</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-bootcamp-week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 15:17:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-bootcamp-week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://casualinferencedotorg.files.wordpress.com/2020/02/bootcamp.jpeg?w=480&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This will be part 2 of 4 in a &lt;strong&gt;weekly series&lt;/strong&gt; focused on preparing for graduate school in STEM if you come from a humanities based undergrad or other graduate experience. Please make sure to follow my blog to get the latest update to the series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://casual-inference.org/2020/02/03/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ideological framework for graduate school&lt;/a&gt;, we ought to shift focus toward our &lt;em&gt;material&lt;/em&gt; environment. This week we will be getting organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting organized is about more than color coding files, printing out a calendar or sticky-notes. Graduate school has the sneaky ability to render any tips and tricks for organization useless. This post will focus on the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;few but wildly important&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; material and environmental factors that contribute to your success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Streamline your finances:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should really be step zero, because it forms the foundation for all other &amp;ldquo;hacks&amp;rdquo; meant to enhance your transition to grad school in STEM. Yet, few students seem to really grasp the day-to-day impact of this lifestyle (speaking peronally as someone who stacked additional loans on tuition just for living expenses). Most of our elders will lecture us about staying frugal, pinching pennies and saving more than we spend, etc. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that 90% of you ignore this, as I did. You have to experience it for yourself before deciding the real importance of decreased spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do this:&lt;/strong&gt; Try to monitor your cash flow as closely as possible for a few days, then try a week. Certain days will inevitably buck the trend, but generally you should be able to estimate what you buy on a bi-weekly basis. Have an honest conversation with yourself about what is essential (&lt;strong&gt;bonus point&lt;/strong&gt;: loop in a close friend or intimate partner) and what is not. The money from your loan will seem like monopoly money at first, so it is vital that you run these pilot spending weeks before this influx of cash. Apps, message boards, and banks can be &lt;em&gt;marginally helpful&lt;/em&gt; but they try to remove friction from spending and tracking finances. You should actively add healthy amounts of friction early on to really see a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Make a scholarship/grant/fellowship action plan&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations if you are already studying at a reduced rate! It not only saves you money, but looks better down the line for interviews and hiring committee review. If not, don&amp;rsquo;t worry- use the first semester of your courses to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;build your case for why you should have been on scholarship in the first place.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you kick butt, &lt;strong&gt;find a free period to do the following&lt;/strong&gt;: Spend an afternoon looking into scholarships (of any amount) that you qualify for, then spend another day to draft and write applications, have them looked over by someone you trust, then submit. Seriously, apply for as many as possible. Dr. Karen Kelsky of &lt;em&gt;The Professor is In&lt;/em&gt; blog and eponymous bestseller advises thousands of students to do this with the goal of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://theprofessorisin.com/2011/07/05/dr-karens-foolproof-grant-template/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;getting on the &amp;ldquo;grant gravy train.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; By getting a foot in the door of the scholarship world, you demonstrate that you are vetted. You&amp;rsquo;ve earned independent, peer-reviewed academic stamps of approval. You are therefore far more likely to be given subsequent scholarships and keep the grant gravy train rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Sort the particulars&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you may have covered some of this last week, it may be worth repeating that straightening out the details of your daily experience will be fundamental to your success. On my first day, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know where to park, where to go for lunch, where my desk would be, or when tuition needed to be paid. These are things that some programs will not hand to you like an orientation leader. Do you know when you can drop a class at the latest to avoid fees? When are your breaks in the semester? Do you have weekend plans or conferences for the fall or spring that need to be prioritized? &lt;strong&gt;Bug your advisor and program coordinator&lt;/strong&gt; about the finer points of your daily and weekly schedule that if mismanaged, can add up to serious degradation of your mental health over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Get (physically) organized&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where do you study? What tools do you need to start working? Don&amp;rsquo;t get to syllabus week and assume that future you will sort this out. Think it through now, open up &lt;em&gt;Amazon&lt;/em&gt; (or your local office supply store, preferably), and buy the binders, file folders, calculators and pens you may need. Some places will offer discounts to students with a valid ID, so make sure to ask for one from your school and start saving money right away. See if your school library offers carrel (private study room) rentals per semester or academic year. Having this (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/2015/03/10/you-are-where-you-work-more-examples-of-fantastically-deep-working-spaces/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;or any quiet, dedicated space&lt;/a&gt;) be your &lt;em&gt;Camp David&lt;/em&gt; of focus will pay huge dividends later in your degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In many ways, material preparation for school can equal the importance of philosophical preparation. Ideas without a plan remain so. However, if you can sort your finances, make a scholarship action plan, sort all the specifics, and get your educational environment organized, you will be well-positioned to succeed in STEM graduate programs and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STEM Grad School Boot-camp: Week 1</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 16:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://casual-inference.org/2020/02/10/dangerous-ideas-should-you-miss-the-max-number-of-classes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dangerous Ideas: Should you miss the max number of classes? – Casual Inferences&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;time datetime=&#34;2020-02-10 10:35:29&#34;&gt;Feb 1, 2020&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] and psychological refreshment will still likely improve your subsequent study. I have already sung its praises in a previous post to think through why you are in school, but it may be even more effective when […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
#### 
[STEM Grad School Bootcamp: Week 2 &amp;#8211; Casual Inferences](http://casual-inference.org/2020/02/12/stem-bootcamp-week-2/ &#34;&#34;) - &lt;time datetime=&#34;2020-02-12 10:17:13&#34;&gt;Feb 3, 2020&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] that we have established our ideological framework for graduate school, we ought to shift focus toward our material environment. This week we will be getting […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
#### 
[STEM Grad School Boot-camp: Week 3 &amp;#8211; Casual Inferences](http://casual-inference.org/2020/02/25/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-3/ &#34;&#34;) - &lt;time datetime=&#34;2020-02-25 10:30:14&#34;&gt;Feb 2, 2020&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] the precision of your planning should be ramping up. We’ve covered everything from the existential to the mundane. It’s time to put pen to paper. Take out a sheet of paper or open your journal […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STEM Grad School Boot-camp: Week 1</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 16:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This will be part 1 of 4 in a &lt;strong&gt;weekly series&lt;/strong&gt; focused on preparing for graduate school in STEM if you come from a humanities based undergrad or other graduate experience. Please make sure to follow my blog to get the latest update to the series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://casualinferencedotorg.files.wordpress.com/2020/02/bootcamp-2.jpeg?w=480&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You did it- you got in! Now what? Entering graduate school can be daunting for some, exciting for others and confusing for most. Unlike day one in undergrad, there are no orientation leaders helping you get your mattress up the stair or guides to walk you to your first class. You need to take full control of the process, which can be both intimidating and empowering. Luckily you are not alone. This blog and a few of my 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://forum.thegradcafe.com/blogs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;favorites&lt;/a&gt;, will lay out the steps needed to take control of your STEM graduate experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Brief caveat: Although I aim to generalize to the sciences, specific fields can vary in direct experience. I hope only that the skills and habits I recommend will give you the tools to transition from the humanities into that field more smoothly.*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week we will cover the what, how and why of your transition. This will be your &lt;strong&gt;big picture week&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thinkers take time to gather their thoughts. Bill Gates famously takes full weeks out of the year to comb through esoteric papers and books in order to frame his actions for the rest of the year. Einstein and Darwin scheduled long walks during their work day. Steve Jobs would habitually walk around the building before launching new Apple Products. Allow yourself space to do the same type of big idea thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you dive into the details of financial aid, classes, and publication plans, ask yourself &lt;em&gt;why.&lt;/em&gt; Generating a &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; for your process will create 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0361476X99910202?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;intrinsic motivation&lt;/a&gt; and feed into your internal 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00256307.1978.12022132&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;locus of control&lt;/a&gt; - a mechanism which may significantly impact your ability to stick with the program even when it gets tough. Think of laying out your &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; as the outline to a term paper. You might lose interest or purpose if you just start rambling about &lt;em&gt;Twelfth Night&lt;/em&gt; and have to address symbols present in five other works of the Bard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to get your why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Option 1:&lt;/em&gt; I have some tried and true methods for uncovering ideas of such depth. The recommended, but not required, ingredients include: a park with trees, shoes, your mind, a significant other, and a dog. You could realistically get along with just the first two, but talking with someone you trust about these big ideas can be really enlightening about your own intentions. &lt;em&gt;Option 2:&lt;/em&gt; Phone a friend. It works on game shows and it works in your life. Your friends probably know you better than you know yourself, and you should be making time to catch up with them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will the process look like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While more detailed than the existential why of graduate school, the what can be just as important. I recommend a five year plan (or at least two) be sketched around a month out from your start. Adopted from Dr. Karen Kelsky&amp;rsquo;s 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://theprofessorisin.com/pearlsofwisdom/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;book and accompanying blog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Professor is In: The Essential Guide to Turning your PhD into a Job&lt;/em&gt;, this plan will give you 1) piece of mind that all deadlines are written down, 2) a tangible finish line, and 3) the same two things for your loved ones. Map out when you start, plan to finish, big life events (marriage? moving?) and holidays then fill in as you (inevitably) collect obligations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all for this week! Check in here to say how your big ideas are flowing- what did you find? What do others in your life think?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
