<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>productivity | Walker Blackston</title>
    <link>https://walkerblackston.com/tag/productivity/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://walkerblackston.com/tag/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>productivity</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://walkerblackston.com/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>productivity</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/tag/productivity/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On working from home dress codes</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/on-working-from-home-dress-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/on-working-from-home-dress-codes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1426523038054-a260f3ef5bc9?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=eyJhcHBfaWQiOjEyMDd9&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1000&amp;amp;q=80&#34; alt=&#34;man wearing blue suit&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About two months ago, we began one of the largest experiments on work and productivity in recent memory. Within the realm of knowledge work, where working from home is most prevalent, we are asked to turn our previous havens of relaxation, comfort, and family time into battle stations whizzing with Zoom meetings and email checks. I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but I find it &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; difficult to separate church and state. I am unfocused at best in my work and detached from family in walks or meal time. Many 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;prominent thinkers in the productivity space&lt;/a&gt; have discussed these issues at length. Many are clearer thinkers and writers than yours truly. But many have perhaps forgotten or unkowingly downsized the importance of &lt;strong&gt;self-presentation&lt;/strong&gt; in establishing new habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that we have subconsciously accepted the narrative of clothing brands in their new ads: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Here are the best sweatpants, slippers and tee-shirts for working from home!&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;(some of the most egregious examples: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.nordstrom.com/c/work-from-home-clothing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.menshealth.com/style/g32037139/work-from-home-clothing-wardrobe-essentials/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/forbes-personal-shopper/2020/04/06/12-of-the-best-work-from-home-athleisure-pieces-for-men/#6657a1063be1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;) While I recognize their market incentive to maintain business, it has created a kind of pathos around the pandemic among other knowledge workers I know who relish in this &amp;ldquo;wear whatever you want,&amp;rdquo; anti-dress-code. &lt;em&gt;But I dissent&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, I decided that I would wear pants and something with buttons up top every day of the work week, and that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t touch or think about work until the last button is fastened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2020/05/kill-the-office-dress-code/609070/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A recent article&lt;/a&gt; in May&amp;rsquo;s edition of &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; called for the eventual destruction of the office dress code as we know it. The author convincingly argues that norms of dress have been restrictive in the past, and perhaps contained a touch of racism or classism. Perhaps some might argue that striving to look a certain way for work destracts from the individual qualities of the worker. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t buy it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.latimes.com/lifestyle/story/2020-04-17/working-from-home-regular-work-wardrobe-dress-up&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;neither does Adam Tschorn of the LA times&lt;/a&gt;). No, I am not advocating for some &lt;em&gt;Mad Men&lt;/em&gt;-esque edict of uniformity (although the qualityt of style in the show is, in my opinion, masterful) that is nostalgic for some idealized condition of society. Rather, I am arguing in favor of &lt;strong&gt;effort&lt;/strong&gt;. Sweatpants at work mean you put in zero effort. Mark Zuckerberg reportedly wore sweatpants to meetings where he intentionally wanted to humiliate his interviewers. The irony is that slipping on sweatpants takes the same amount of time as buttoning khakis or jeans, at least for men. My fiance agrees with me on this— maybe hair and makeup add time over the sweatpant approach, but not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; much more time. At the least, putting in effort to your dress during this time might give you confidence and a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/heapro/article/28/2/166/661129&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sense of control that we crave&lt;/a&gt; as creatures of habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if putting on that belt or that shirt was like priming your workout habit by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/17437199.2013.876238#.U7YQgY1dUWs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;simply putting on your running shoes, or hailing a cab?&lt;/a&gt; These are commonly labeled as &amp;ldquo;hacks&amp;rdquo; but should really be seen as prequels to the habit itself. These are like the appetizers for whatever habit you want to take home for dinner. Want to establish a morning writing habit? Make putting on your &amp;ldquo;work clothes&amp;rdquo; and sitting down, outlining or even (my personal &amp;ldquo;appetizer&amp;rdquo;) turning on a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://thebankerslamp.com/what-is/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;banker&amp;rsquo;s lamp&lt;/a&gt; to show yourself what &amp;ldquo;writing you&amp;rdquo; looks like in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above all, let&amp;rsquo;s face it: we want to relish in the ability to wear sweatpants when we&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; clocked out. We want the feeling of putting them on to trigger thoughts of a good movie, book, or family meal —not of a full work day ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seneca at the photocopier: Practicing stoicism as an graduate intern</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/seneca-at-the-photocopier-practicing-stoicism-as-an-graduate-intern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 19:47:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/seneca-at-the-photocopier-practicing-stoicism-as-an-graduate-intern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Worthy punches the elevator call button as a steaming cup of Folgers sloshes onto his naked wrist. His punishment for lateness is compounded by his perception of today&amp;rsquo;s upcoming duties. As he sidles to the back corner of the elevator pod, he turns to scan the announcement board. He remains turned with each floor passing, effectively ignoring incoming passengers. He gets off at 11 and unlocks the door with his free hand. After crashing into his swivel chair, he makes way to &lt;em&gt;the binder&lt;/em&gt;. The binder holds his duties, his wants and dreams for the next 4 hours. After initially making peace with the binder, Jack runs down the list of reasons why this all sucks. He deserves better - isn&amp;rsquo;t he a little old to be doing this? He&amp;rsquo;s more than educated enough to get &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;else&lt;/em&gt; to do it (I mean, he is a &lt;em&gt;graduate&lt;/em&gt; student after all). He was late and no one noticed! Surely he&amp;rsquo;s not that important if that&amp;rsquo;s true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bored with complaining, Jack made his way to the copier. He would need to unbuckle the first however-many sheets, line them up, enter his email address, ensure that the file name would reflect the purpose and genre of the sheets in transit and punch &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Start&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo; He would bring a book or something to do while the machine did its thing, but it often jammed unpredictably. He realized that any more than 20 pages at a time would be a risk. Also, sheets were frequently out of order. A CRF might be mingled with a PHI, and a consent form sprinkled in the middle of MEQs or RFAs. So he developed a system of binder clips to allow for easier bindering and organizing down the line. He felt a bit dubious for thinking this &amp;ldquo;innovation&amp;rdquo; would increase his productivity (what did it mean to be more productive at &lt;em&gt;scanning&lt;/em&gt;?) but the added free time was nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very slowly then all at once, Jack felt calm. Succeeding at a game he created (how can he scan more records more efficiently and cleanly?), the frame of his administrative duties had flipped. He was more than accepting of its banality, he was &lt;em&gt;grateful.&lt;/em&gt;..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Worthy does not exist. He is a fictional account of my first day as a student intern in a local health clinic&amp;rsquo;s office of records. His realization of gratitude mirrors my own after reading William Irvine&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Stoic Challenge&lt;/em&gt;, Professor Irvine invokes the stoics, a set of philosophers from antiquity interested in bringing balance and tranquility to their way of life. Far from being debbie-downers, the stoics took great joy in life as they frequently visualized life &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; its most joyful components. The quick glance into a poverty of good stuff or good relationships made their reality a miracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irvine&amp;rsquo;s main piece of homework, the &amp;ldquo;stoic test strategy&amp;rdquo; asks that we treat each of life&amp;rsquo;s setbacks as we would an exam: how did we react to them emotionally and logistically? Only if we found a reasonable solution, and did so without anger or frustration can we call it a pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day, I decided to take Irvine to task. I would test both my overall performance on the day and sprinkle in sub-tests for tasks that would be particularly trying of my patience. I thought it might help pass the time or make me seem at least &lt;em&gt;outwardly&lt;/em&gt; pleasant. I did not expect, however, for it to create an overwhelming sense of calm and gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now on the hunt to talk with anyone and everyone who&amp;rsquo;s been in my shoes. How have you taken this opportunity to do more than &amp;ldquo;get through&amp;rdquo; something? Depsite seemingly exponential progress in machine learning, I doubt AIs will be scanning, filing and redacting our old paper copy medical records in the next decade. They certainly won&amp;rsquo;t be calling participants to check on them (unless they expect to get hung up on). A significant portion of our economy still centers on administrative tasks &amp;ndash; some estimate as many as millions of people still serve to categorize, store and move information. How might adopting a stoical philosophy reframe this activity for us who think that we have &amp;ldquo;better things&amp;rdquo; to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think- How have you handled the burden of menial tasks? How would the &amp;ldquo;stoic gods&amp;rdquo; have thought you performed in doing so?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STEM Grad School Boot-camp: Week 3</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://casualinferencedotorg.files.wordpress.com/2020/02/bootcamp-2.jpeg?w=480&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This will be part 3 of 4 in a &lt;strong&gt;weekly series&lt;/strong&gt; focused on preparing for graduate school in STEM if you come from a humanities based undergrad or other graduate experience. Please make sure to follow my blog to get the latest update to the series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;We must believe that we are gifted for something and that this thing, at whatever cost, must be attained.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; - Marie Curie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impetus for a &amp;ldquo;big project&amp;rdquo; has pushed even the most stuck thinkers and writers of our time into the realm of productivity. While the particulars of each approach differ- JK Rowlings used to book luxury hotel rooms for the self-imposted financial pressure- the common thread of a &amp;ldquo;big project&amp;rdquo; remains. I propose that this type of project would exponentially improve your graduate experience (and subsequent job hunt). This week, we will be planning out our &amp;ldquo;big project,&amp;rdquo; or the one thing that if you finished it this semester or academic year would confer immense benefits to your career. This project comes with &lt;strong&gt;just two basic ground rules&lt;/strong&gt; that, if followed, should confer these exponential benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) It should be both easy to describe and plan but hard to execute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you are weeks from starting your STEM graduate experience, the precision of your planning should be ramping up. We&amp;rsquo;ve covered everything from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://casual-inference.org/2020/02/03/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;existential&lt;/a&gt; to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://casual-inference.org/2020/02/12/stem-bootcamp-week-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mundane&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s time to put pen to paper. &lt;strong&gt;Take out a sheet of paper or open your journal and write down the following:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;what would I be most proud of myself for doing this year?&lt;/em&gt; Make sure this is related to graduate school, but not necessarily grades or GPA focused. By this, I mean, try not to write about getting a 4.0. While this is a great accomplishment, most employers and even PhD programs think in terms of grade bands. A 4.0 is nice, but not as weighty as it was in undergrad. It might be expected in some rare instances or institutions (check first), but a 3.5-3.7 may carry similar assurances of competency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;focus on planning something that the other students (who are chasing the 4.0) are not considering&lt;/strong&gt;. Can you get on a peer-reviewed scientific manuscript or conference abstract? Can you co-write a computer program with an advisor or advanced PhD student? Are there skills that are not being taught in your program you could pick up and organize into a brief seminar for faculty and staff? These are flexible win-wins - even the &lt;em&gt;efforts&lt;/em&gt; to produce deliverables as code or a paper increase your skills in the area and often lead to better letters of recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) It&amp;rsquo;s what you work on first.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This next rule will certainly get me in trouble with your advisor and lecturers. However, if executed properly, should leave you in good shape for their classes in addition to your goals. This project should be the focus of that first chunk of study time during the day. When you are fresh and most likely to hang on to your attention , this time period becomes critical to advance the goals of your project. Even if you are in a lull and waiting on feedback from others, commit 30 minutes to planning your next moves. How will you approach feedback from this person? Should you meet with them personally (or over Skype) to discuss? Make a schedule to chip away and make your big project seem smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/em&gt; If planned carefully and attacked consistently, the big project could catapult your STEM graduate school experience into career success. Many careers follow exponential curves for success - marginal gains creep forward from hard work until they explode into life-altering achievement. The &amp;ldquo;big project&amp;rdquo; is a way to skip the plateau phase. In the same way that grants beget more grants, papers beget more papers and scientific expertise begets more scientific expertise. Make the moonshots now and you will reap rewards later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stay tuned for the &lt;strong&gt;final week of STEM Grad school boot-camp,&lt;/strong&gt; where we will be fine tuning some day-to-day habits guaranteed to transition you fully from humanities to STEM!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dangerous Ideas: Should you miss the max number of classes?</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/dangerous-ideas-should-you-miss-the-max-number-of-classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/dangerous-ideas-should-you-miss-the-max-number-of-classes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://casualinferencedotorg.files.wordpress.com/2020/02/photo-1576673195444-be906d7012d3-1.jpeg?w=1024&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Credit: Austrian National Library&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a feeling familiar to any student: You sit through lecture for an approximate eternity, pondering the infinite other ways to spend your time. Maybe you are not one to miss, let alone skip, classes that may cost hundreds of dollars per lecture. Maybe you really want to do well or even feel that you owe the professor enough respect for an hour of your attention (more of us should think this way, but that&amp;rsquo;s another topic of discussion). Regardless of your intention, your attention fades. Experiencing this myself, I asked a more global question: &lt;em&gt;what if I missed this lecture, then lectured and tested myself on the same material?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s evaluate this question empirically, because we can guess the subjective answer is a definitive &lt;em&gt;yes.&lt;/em&gt; I will make &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;three primary arguments&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in favor of missing the maximum allowable lectures from your course syllabus (this is usually under the attendance heading).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;CAVEAT:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This argument assumes that you are in STEM-focused, technical or semi-technical classes. If lecture or discussion material are exclusively covered as they are in a non-technical class, I would not advise this strategy.*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;Lectures do not typically feature problem sets - which are fundamental to your success in a technical course.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prevailing wisdom among scholars of learning suggests that active recall - the act of reading a question, looking away to answer, and checking your answer with the correct answer - cements deeper chunks of knowledge in our brains. This method is the most efficient for shifting knowledge from short-term and/or working memory to long-term memory. Hearing a professor describe a formula or method is one thing, but moving the pieces around with your mind is another. In fact, hearing something described can sometimes create the paradoxical effect of &amp;ldquo;display learning (term my own)&amp;quot;, where you feel the sense of familiarity with a topic overshadow the deeper intuition required to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; and reproduce it on a test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Lectures can be distracting environments and hamper deeper learning of concepts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am lucky in that I have never had to endure massive lecture halls filled with hungover students infinitely swiping across their suite of social media apps. I&amp;rsquo;ve had the rare fortune of small class sizes (or favorable &amp;ldquo;student:teacher ratios&amp;rdquo; in the higher ed world) where distraction can be hemmed by social pressures. However, the modern lecture is filled with distractions, regardless of size. Next time you are in class, take stock of how many people take notes for a few minutes then flit away to whatever shinier site or app piques their interest. I personally don&amp;rsquo;t care how people choose to spend their time or money. The residual distraction for others is what bothers me. If anything, missing some lectures may come with some added mental health benefits- provided you use the time gained wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t go anywhere (and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1455586692/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1455509124&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=stuhac-20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;should&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;All truly great thoughts are conceived by walking&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you, but my best head space is found on foot. Walking around brings an almost instantaneous shot of mental clarity that it&amp;rsquo;s surprising we have not attempted to hold lectures on the go (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you, organizational and learning psychologists..). However, I am not alone. Centuries of big thinkers attributed their success and clarity to bouts of lengthy walks. While I have my doubts on the utility of praising Nietzsche, it is true that he would actively schedule long walks to lay out arguments or treatises for his work. Einstein and Darwin are reported to have done the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you fail to work through your target concept, the physical and psychological refreshment will still likely improve your subsequent study. I have already 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://casual-inference.org/2020/02/03/stem-grad-school-boot-camp-week-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sung its praises&lt;/a&gt; in a previous post to think through why you are in school, but it may be even more effective when wrestling big lecture topics or problem sets. I even find that taking a drive by yourself with no music or podcasts can uncover similar clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Words of caution and next steps:&lt;/strong&gt; All of these arguments are testable and falsifiable. If you find that missing lectures puts you behind the 8-ball on course material, don&amp;rsquo;t do it! Also, if you don&amp;rsquo;t trust yourself to spend this time gained wisely, don&amp;rsquo;t do it! Only if you feel like you can stow away to a quiet space and push your knowledge deeply should you miss class. In a sense, you&amp;rsquo;re trusting yourself to be the professor for a class of one- do so with care and attention and you may just reap the rewards of deeper understanding and more free time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special Topics: Reading Scientific Manuscripts</title>
      <link>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/special-topics-reading-scientific-manuscripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 15:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://walkerblackston.com/blog/special-topics-reading-scientific-manuscripts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@roman_lazygeek?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Roman Mager&lt;/a&gt; on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/chalkboard?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;_“It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how beautiful your theory is, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how smart you are. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t agree with experiment, it&amp;rsquo;s wrong.” _&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Richard Fenyman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like it or not, publishing a scientific article 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/350/6256/49&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;remains&lt;/a&gt; the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3999612/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;primary productivity metric for academic researchers&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3999612/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Publish or perish&amp;rdquo; is no joke&lt;/a&gt; (and the name of a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://harzing.com/resources/publish-or-perish&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;great citation tracker&lt;/a&gt;). Even outside of academia, the ability to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencemag.org/careers/2012/09/so-you-think-you-have-skills&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;quickly synthesize and extract information from these papers will provide necessary context&lt;/a&gt; for your work in the field. Numerous scholars have 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencemag.org/careers/2016/03/how-seriously-read-scientific-paper&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;opined on the best way to learn this process&lt;/a&gt; . But they are likely coming from a related technical field. We are humanities folks. We can ponder the racial theory of Vonnegut one day, and the feminist critiques of Dickinson another. I would argue, however, less domain specific knowledge is needed to “get” a scientific article than you think. Regardless of field, I propose the following 5 steps &lt;strong&gt;to drastically improve your reading time and knowledge obtained&lt;/strong&gt; from each manuscript:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Read backwards.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to a journalist in a major periodical, scientists have, generally, one &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;big idea&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; they wish to convey to their audience. All that changes are the methods. Instead of extended metaphors and wordplay, we deal in variables, study designs, and causal pathways. Because the arc of the story remains consistent, I recommend that beginners &lt;strong&gt;start with the conclusion of a scientific article.&lt;/strong&gt; This will ensure two things: (1) you have a “big picture” of the story the authors are telling, and (2) you can more easily predict how they conducted their experiment(s). This is like skipping ahead to the punchline of a joke—sure, it ruins the suspense, but it gives you the main ideas all at once [re-work this metaphor]. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before moving to our next step, quickly glance at any &lt;em&gt;sources of funding mentioned after the conclusion&lt;/em&gt;. There are heated ongoing debates whether this belongs in science (I remain neutral as we do not have enough data yet to determine its influence and each source is different), but it can help you understand why the work is being done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) &lt;strong&gt;Stop. Take two minutes to guess what comes next.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, this is weird. You wouldn’t pick up &lt;em&gt;The Sun Also Rises,&lt;/em&gt; read “&lt;em&gt;Isn’t it pretty to think so&lt;/em&gt;,” and then stop to think about how Hemingway set the stage. But this isn’t Hemingway. We can expect certain things to be said from science papers. If this is literally your first scientific article, &lt;em&gt;take a stab!&lt;/em&gt; You will be surprised how well your guess matches the methods presented. Write this guess down in the margin and move to step three. Making it this far means you have committed to the broader scientific process of hypothesize, test, feedback and repeat - a process growing in popularity 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2019/03/18/5-strategies-ace-exam/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;among study hacking circles.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;strong&gt;Read the introduction deeply.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This advice also runs counter to conventional wisdom which tells you to more or less skim the introduction . This is wise for &lt;em&gt;experienced scientists&lt;/em&gt; who only need to extract some context before plunging into the methods and results. You need it all. Be looking for how they discuss certain phenomenon—how do they phrase what they know? Is a relationship already established (“&lt;em&gt;we know X influences Y&lt;/em&gt;”)? Is it unclear (“&lt;em&gt;it is likely that&lt;/em&gt; X” or &lt;em&gt;“emerging evidence suggests that Y”)&lt;/em&gt;? Context for the narrative will come. You need to meticulously pick out their linguistic tools. As you finish this close reading, circle concepts or phenomena of interest or confusion (for later articles!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) &lt;strong&gt;Skim the methods and results.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods and results are the cash cow of most scientific papers[cite]. Here I propose another tactic that departs from conventional wisdom. However, for &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; purposes, beginners need context and process more than getting bogged down in the details. Trying to read this section for comprehension early on is like reading senior theses in your freshman seminar. Instead, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/2017/08/14/how-i-read-when-researching-a-book/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;circle&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;draw&lt;/strong&gt; arrows to concepts you would like to eventually learn.&lt;/a&gt; This accomplishes two things: it primes you for actually learning them more deeply later, and it gives you a starting place to read more papers in the field. If you feel like you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to cover some of the results, focus on whatever they present in the first paragraph of the results section. This will typically offer a statistical summary of their findings supporting the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;big idea.&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5) &lt;strong&gt;Read the discussion like a play.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve taken an acting class or seen a live play (given you are trained in the humanities, this is a fair assumption) you know that almost all plays follow a formula. They contain characters, setting, dialogue and a resolution divided into acts. Science trades in variables, samples, comparison and discussion to deliver its biggest ideas. Framing a scientific manuscript as a play provides a solid framework to maintain comprehension in the face of difficult language or math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, when I was first reading articles on survival analysis, I imagined the hazard ratio (change in survival over change in time) as an old-timey, sepia-toned scene where someone was stitching together tons of snapshot pictures for an overall movie of a dance. If you took one picture it would give you information on what the dancers were doing at the &lt;em&gt;precise&lt;/em&gt; instant they were photographed, conditioned that they were still dancing. Swap out dancers for patients in a cardiothoracic surgery clinic, and the concept holds true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to extract useful information from scientific manuscripts touches many careers in and outside of science. Most importantly, if done in what I am calling the &lt;strong&gt;storytelling framework&lt;/strong&gt;, it will connect you to our most ancient trades and practices as a species. Try it out and let me know how it goes in the comments below! What worked and what didn&amp;rsquo;t?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
